Now that's a contract. But we still don't have a database.
Our database class will extend an Android class. SQLITEOpenHELPER.
SQLITEOpenHELPER contains cool stuff to help us handle database versioning.
As we make changes to our database in the future, it will help us modify our
tables. For many apps, being able to upgrade to a new version without data loss
is critical. Let's create a WeatherDBHelper class within the data package and
have that extend SQLite Open Helper. [SOUND] We can add
the required methods by hitting Ctrl+I.
And we can override the constructor by hitting Ctrl+O. So now we can hard code
these variables to constructor. Hard coding name to database name,
our factory to null, and our version to database version.
Now, you'll note I have made the database name public, and
that's because we're going to use it in our tests in the future.
Now you see we've got it on create and an onUpgrade method.
In the OnCreate method, we're going to start by creating a string to build
the weather entry table using data defined within the weather entry contract.
Now I'm just going to add this comment, so you know where to go back and
add the location entry stuff later. Since weather entry depends on
location entry, I would normally write location entry first, but
weather entry is pretty complicated. So I'd rather explain what we've done and
leave location entry up to you. We're going to use raw SQL for
our create table query, beginning with the table name from our contract.
At this point, it's helpful to import WeatherContract.locationentry and
weather entry. It makes our query so much easier to read. We'll start with
our ID field, which we'll set as our primary key in an auto increment field.
Note that integer is actually a signed value up to eight bytes long in SQLite.
Using the auto increment feature doesn't do precisely what one might think.
Setting up the ID is an integer primary key actually makes
the value unique whenever you do an insert, but it may not always increment.
It may reuse existing ID values of the records have been deleted.
What autoincrement is really useful for, is if you're synchronizing data two
ways with the server. But, we'll take advantage of it here because it makes data
from our queries sort a bit more naturally because we insert them in the right
order coming from the server. In general, we're using constraints on fields.
In this case, not null. We do this because it allows the database to do much of
our parameter validation for us. The tricky part about doing it this way,
is that we don't get useful errors when these constraints fail, so
it can be challenging to debug. We're using a human readable string for
the date. There's no strong reason for or
against this choice. We wanted to normalize the date to simplify our queries,
and human readability simplifies debugging. The date comes from open weather in
Unix time stamp format with some time information that we need to get rid of.
I'm not going to cover every field. Real means floating point in SQL.
It would have been fine to have used integer with fixed point math as well and
some would argue that this would be faster, but
real is more straight forward since we're storing floating point values. Now for
the fun stuff, we're going to set up a loc key.
It's a foreign key to the location entry table that you will be building.
This causes SQLite to enforce the relationship between the tables.
We cannot insert a weather entry when there is no corresponding location entry.
And we cannot delete a location entry if there are still weather entries that
depend on it. Cool stuff, right? One last constraint.
Our date text plus location must be unique. On conflict, replace the data.
This allows us to insert new data from the open weather EPI easily.
Preserving existing keys and updating the value as the forecast changes.